This דף *daf* is ע"ז *Ayin Zayin*, 77, and we are the
last דף *daf* of בהמה המקשה *Behema Hamakasha* which this whole פרק
Perek *perek* devoted to animals and childbirth and שחיטה shechting *shechting* an
animal with a fetus in the womb other than yesterday where we
had what seemed to be a misplacing from טריפות *Treifos*, טריפות *Treifos*.
We pick up on the top of ע"ז *Ayin Zayin* עמוד א'
Amud Aleph, *Amud Aleph*, actually a few lines ahead,
and now we pick up with, okay, נשבר העצם *Nishbar ha-etzem*. It
is one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight lines down. Line
starts with word יחיד *Yachid* and we are near the end of
the line, נשבר העצם *Nishbar ha-etzem*. All right, so נשבר העצם *Nishbar
ha-etzem*, if the bone broke, which was the case in the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah*, that if the leg, the bone of the leg broke
and it was dangling, depending on where the break was, it could
either make the animal a טריפה treifah, *treifa* or at least mean
that if that limb was dangling and you שחיטה shechitah, *shechted* the
animal you couldn't eat the leg. However, the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* gave
the exception: what would happen if the bone, if the break, it
was covered with the flesh of the leg, of the limb? Then
the break would not be a problem. So we're going to talk
about exactly, we talked about yesterday,
how to define when the flesh covers the break, and we're going
to continue exploring some of those cases now. So let's take a
look. נשבר העצם ויצא לחוץ *Nishbar ha-etzem ve-yatza lachutz*, the bone broke
and it's protruding on the outside. But ואשתקיל קורתא מיניה *ve-ishtakeil korta
minei*,
okay, and a little bit of ההוא *hahu*, I'm sorry, I should
have started with word ההוא *hahu*. There was a case, ההוא נשבר
העצם ויצא לחוץ *hahu nishbar ha-etzem ve-yatza lachutz*. There was a certain
case where an animal, whether it was I don't know a chicken
or a cow, the bone broke and a piece came and was
protruding, ואשתקיל קורתא מיניה *ve-ishtakeil korta minei*, and a little piece of
the bone had fallen off. So we hadn't discussed that case in
the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. The משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* just spoke about a
break and if the break is being covered with the flesh, that
can counteract it. But let's say in addition to the break, a
little part of the bone actually chipped off.
If this was covered with flesh or no,
well, apparently it was, or else it wouldn't have been a question.
So let's take a look. אתא לקמיה דאביי *ata lekamei de-Abaye*, this
case was brought in front of אביי Abaye, *Abaye*. שהייה תלתא ריגלי
*shehayah telasa riglei*, he held it over for three רגלים *regalim*. I
don't think that's a pun, but anyway he held it over for
three for the
to keep on to ask people that would gather together for the
רגלים *regalim*. Now this is a little bit bizarre, first of all
exactly, first of all the case is that what do you do
with the meat in the interim? But maybe they had מוקצה *muktzah*,
they did preserve their meat in salt, so maybe you still went
ahead and you preserved it, you know, you made it into beef
jerky or whatever they did in order to preserve it. Okay, I
guess it never really occurred to me how long you could preserve
meat when you were doing it with salt, but I mean it's
like salami, right? Right, how long can salami last? It can last
a long, long time, right? So anyway, okay. The other interesting thing
is that here they are in בבל *Bavel* and somehow the idea,
I mean if the רגלים *regalim* is meant to signify something, not
just a year, but the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* suggests is people
gather together in the רגלים *regalim*, so it gives him an opportunity
to ask other people. They're not gathering in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* on the
רגלים *regalim*, right? So wherever they're, I mean so it still is
interesting that it suggests these various gatherings that would take place during
the רגלים *regalim*, if that's what it's meant to signify. Anyway, to
try to figure out what the answer to this was. אמר ליה
amar lei רב אדא בר מתנה *amar lei Rav Adda bar Matna*,
so רב אדא בר מתנה *Rav Adda bar Matna* said to him,
interesting רש"י Rashi *Rashi* said the him here isn't אביי Abaye, *Abaye*,
the him here was the owner of the animal.
זיל לקמיה דרבא בריה דרב יוסף בר חמא *zel lekamei de-Rava breih
de-Rav Yosef bar Chama*, the son of
חמא *Chama*, דחריפא סכיניה *de-charifa sakinah*, he has a sharp knife, which
is obviously like a bit of a metaphor, meaning he's very sharp
and analytical and he'll be able to maybe give you an answer
because אביי *Abaye* isn't getting an answer for you, which is interesting.
אתא לקמיה *ata lekamei*, he went in front of him. אמר *amar*
and he said, מכדי Michdi, *michti*, let's take a look. נשבר העצם
ויצא לחוץ תנן *nishbar ha-etzem ve-yatza lachutz tenan*, our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
says if the bone broke and it protrudes on the outside, and
the question is, actually תניא *tanya* because the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* didn't
use the word protrude, but anyway, and then the question is that
whether it is covered with, you know, with the flesh or not.
So he says, it just says straight if it breaks and goes,
if it breaks and protrudes, מה לי נפל מה לי איתא *mah
li nafal mah li issa*, what difference does it make if a
piece of bone broke off or not? The משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* does
not make any distinction. Now you are I guess expecting something a
little, okay, it's a good point, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* just says
it, it doesn't distinguish, so it sounds like in whatever case it
is, as long as the flesh is covering it, it's okay. But
given that he was sort of told go to him, he's got
a really, you know, sharp knife or a really like, you know,
piercing intellect, you might have expected some, you know, deeper analysis than
just the point that the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* doesn't distinguish. But anyway,
he felt that was enough to rely upon, and therefore even if
a little bit of the bone chipped off, as long as the
flesh surrounds it, it's okay. Yes, Charlie.
So it's okay if we don't get any answer at all from
the person we
asked?
That is a good point. That would be, I mean again, it's
a little funny that רש״י Rashi says that when he said go
ask, he was talking to the person asking rather than to אביי,
you might have expected him to talk to אביי, but I guess
it's yeah I guess the אמר ליה I don't know somehow the
exchange at the end did sort of sound more like he was
ruling for the questioner rather than responding to a colleague's query. But
yeah, you know, if a if you're not I mean the הלכה
halacha is that if you get a פסק psak you can't go
ahead and ask for another פסק psak from someone else, but he
didn't get a פסק. psak. Yeah, so he said let me ask,
let me try to refer.
Same case in that famous case
five years ago where רב שמעון בן יוחאי Rav Shimon ben Yochai
did that.
Five years ago in the דף יומי. Daf Yomi. Oh, five years
ago in the דף יומי. Daf Yomi.
Okay, I was wondering. All right.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, all right. אמר ליה
רבינא לרבא. amar lei Ravina l'Rava. So רבינא Ravina said to רבא.
Rava. מסלקת מהו. mislaket mahu. So although we were up until now
talking about a problem that the bone had chipped, the context here
רש״י Rashi says makes it sound like we're not talking about questions
about how much of you know the status of the flesh that's
surrounding the bone that counteracts the break. What let's say that flesh
surrounds the bone the majority of it but not in one place.
מסלקת mislaket means like you know you have to collect it meaning
a little bit surrounded here a little there and there are you
know there are gaps in the flesh where the bone is exposed
and where the break is exposed. Or it's not it's not in
one you know
contiguous area that it's being surrounded by the flesh.
And the same thing, משנה mishna, doesn't say it has to all
be in one place.
I know, I know, it's funny like exactly that. Right. You know,
משרוסות מהו. mishrosos mahu. What if it is what if the flesh
is thinned out meaning it's not what meaning it's like it is
surrounding the flesh but not the full thickness it's surrounding the break
but not the full thickness of the flesh if you know it's
been like worn away so you only have a very thin layer
of flesh. מסמסות מהו. mismasas mahu. What if it is what if
the flesh is actually sort of rotting away? It's surrounding the break
but it's rotting away. So היכי דמי מסמסות? heichi dami mismasas? What
would be that case? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע amar Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua כל שהרופא קודרו. kol she'arofe kodro. Anything that
a doctor would sort of like you know remove. It's basically such
rotting flesh that the doctor would take it away. Is that still
considered flesh to protect against the break? And the גמרא Gemara does
not give an answer to any of that. איבעיא להו. itba'u lehu.
And then another question was asked. ניקב מהו. nikev mahu. Let's say
there are holes in the flesh. Like okay, when we say that
most of the flesh is surrounding the break, presumably it means not
all the flesh because the the bone has broken and some of
it has protruded away from the flesh. But let's say actually there
are holes in the flesh that have either either spread the flesh
out or maybe removed a piece of it. רש״י Rashi would say
it's even a hole that has not actually taken away any of
the flesh. But it's enough but the point is that maybe because
it's not sort of the natural way the flesh exists right? There's
a hole in in the flesh. Maybe that should somehow be a
problem.
But just one little hole?
I know, it's a funny question given the radical more you know
more drastic situations we were describing before. I agree it is a
little strange.
נקלף מהו. niklaf mahu. Let's say it is peeled. Now the way
רש״י explains this, it means that yes you have flesh around the
bone where the break is, but it's not sort of it's not
adhering to the bone. It's been peeled away from the bone so
it's sitting on top of the break but it's not actually you
know it's cleaving to the bone itself. Obviously you would think that
that would be a lot less significant in sort of counteracting the
significance of the break.
נסדק מהו. nisdak mahu. Let's say it is cracked, which is more
similar to the question of of the hole, which is that the
flesh is there but there are cracks in the hole. Well maybe
again the crack maybe the cracks in the flesh mean the cracks
in the hole. The concern was getting back to Michael's question, why
is that such a big deal since it's basically all connected, is
maybe there's a sense that that will spread and mean that the
flesh will remove itself from the bone. So what are those? ניטש
שלישא תחתון מהו. nitosh tlisha tachton mahu. Let's say the bottom third
is removed, which is similar to the case of נקלף niklaf but
more drastic. Which is נקלף niklaf is you have the whole thickness
of the flesh on the bone but it's not connected. Let's say
the bottom part of the flesh is removed so you have the
flesh still sitting on the bone but number one it's not connected
and number two it's only like the top half, you know, some
the thickness has been cut has been cut down, the bottom thickness
has been removed. In all these cases does it counteract the break?
So תא שמע. ta shma. Come and hear. דאמר עולא אמר רבי
יוחנן d'amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan עור הרי הוא כבשר. or harei
hu kevasar. That was a ברייתא braita we introduced yesterday or a
statement we introduced yesterday, which is that the skin counts instead of
the flesh as a substitute to the flesh. So even if the
flesh isn't adhering to the bone, if the skin is adhering to
the bone that's enough. So that should at least answer some of
our questions because if it's just the skin what
what is skin and what is flesh?
Well actually it's a good point. For humans is there a big
difference between your outer layer of skin and the and the flesh
underneath it? But if you think about a cow you've got the
layer that's the leather, right, that's the hard hide, and then you
have the flesh part that's the meat.
Right, same thing for humans. Yeah okay.
It's probably just not as not as big of a difference
in terms
of
A chicken, right, when you remove the skin of the chicken, people
that, right, that skin the chicken, there's a layer of skin before
you get to the meat. So, we said yesterday that if the
skin covers the break, even if the meat does not, that's considered
a covering of the break. So the גמרא Gemara says, oh look,
that's certainly similar to our case about what happens if the skin
is detached from the bone, or if
some of the thickness of the skin is removed and only the
top level of thickness remains, because the case of the skin, it's
not attached to the bone, it's not the whole thickness of the
skin, and nonetheless that counts to protect against the break. So isn't
that analogous to the case that we just raised? That's what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says no, there could be
a difference. What could be the difference? דילמא דקנא משכא דידיה. dilma
dekana mashka didei. Maybe רש"י's Rashi גירסא girsa is דקנא, dekana, תוספות's
Tosafot גירסא girsa is ריקנא rikna or something, but רש"י Rashi means
it purchased, it's purchasing or holding onto its own skin. What does
that mean? He means we don't mean there are places where the
bone does not really have flesh around it, but it has skin
around it, like if you think about your knee joint. Somebody's gonna
have to, this is not really fully active, but feel right by
your knee joint, right under that layer of skin is the bone,
right as opposed to feel on your side, you can't feel your
leg bone through your thigh, right, but you can feel your knee
bone through your knee. So where it says that the skin counts,
it's where the skin is adhering to the bone and is directly
attached to the bone. Our question was, so we don't need a
thick layer as long as in that place it's naturally adhering, that
will be considered to protect it. But where there is flesh and
some of the flesh has been
removed from the bone and is just sitting on top of it,
or you don't even have the full thickness and it's not adhering
to the bone, that's our question about whether that counteracts the break.
Okay.
I just want to say there's a real good example is your
shin. Try not to ever have an accident with your shin because
it's
right by the bone and it's very hard to heal.
I once had
to have a skin transplant as part...
huh, interesting. Also your like ankle I imagine, right, the skin goes
right over the bone there, yeah. Okay.
All right. I mean yeah, there are other parts of your body
also, like your nose or I mean right, there are other parts
of your body that the skin is basically right on top of
the bone, so there's not really too much flesh around it. Okay.
All right, so איבעיא, ibaia, I'm sorry, no, so now the גמרא
Gemara is okay. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, כי הוינא בי
רב פפי, ki havina be Rav Papi, when I was in the
house of רב פפי, Rav Papi, איבעיא לן. ibaia lan. We asked
the following question: נקדר כמין טבעת מהו? nikdar k'min tabaat mahu? Let's
say there's a hole in it like a ring, which is a
little bit interesting, how is that so much different than the previous
question of a hole? But okay, it's like a significantly sized hole.
And רש"י Rashi says we're still assuming the majority of the break
is covered, but maybe if you make such a big hole in
one area, that will, you know, that sort of undermines the entire
protection of the covering. ופשטינה u'pashtina and we concluded it מהא דאמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, me'ha d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, דבר זה
שאלתי לחכמים ולרופאים. davar zeh sha'alti lachachamim u'larofim. I asked the sages
and the doctors. Notice that, there you go. Okay, what is, meaning
how if you have a break and some of the flesh has
been removed, like a hole cut away, can it still heal? ואמרו
v'amru and here's what they said to me: מסרטו בעצם ומעלה ארוכה.
mesarto b'etzem u'ma'ala arucha. If you basically scratch it with a bone
and cause it to bleed the way רש"י Rashi says, you cause
it to bleed and then you cause it to, you know, that
will cause, the bleeding will basically, you know, and the pus or
whatever will fill the hole and then it'll harden and then it'll
cause it actually to, you know, to heal, to regenerate. So actually
there is a way that even with that type of a hole,
it can get a scab and it can heal. אבל פרזלא, aval
parzla, but if you were to use a knife to try to
do that thing, to scrape it and to get it to bleed
and to scab, מזרז זריף. mizraz zarif. That would actually, you know,
that would make incisions and that would actually be counterproductive. That wouldn't
help. But presumably the answer is, since under some circumstances even with
this hole it can scab and heal over, then even in this
circumstance the meat is considered to protect the bone and to counteract
the break in the bone. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, והוא
דקנא גרמא דידיה. v'hu dekana garma didei. Again this phrase which רש"י
Rashi says means as long as it is still adhering to its
bone, as long as the flesh is still adhering to the bone.
If the flesh is not adhering to the bone and it's just
sitting on top of it, then it would not have the same
counteractive effects. Let me just check רש"י Rashi one second. Right. Okay.
רש"י Rashi also says that if you see that it's sort of
cleaving right around where the hole is, you also see that it's
in the process of scabbing and healing over and- So all of
this was just to deal with the משנה. mishna, The whole purpose
of this משנה's Mishnah doing in our פרק Perek is our פרק's
Perek. been talking about a limb growing out from a fetus and
when you שחט shecht the mother the status of the limb. So
our משנה Mishna dealt with a case of a dangling limb of
the mother of an animal itself as a similar status, and if
you שחט shecht the mother, you שחט shecht the animal I should
say, the dangling limb can't be eaten. However, as a result of
that we wound up discussing, you know, what makes dangling? So it
has to be broken, not detached, broken but not surrounded by flesh.
If it's surrounded by flesh, we're trying to figure out here how
much surrounded by flesh and what the exact parameters of that are,
but if it's broken, look at what the camera just did because
I moved out of... anyway, but if it's broken then it, what
do you call it, then it... sorry let me just fix this.
Anyway, anyway, but if it's broken and surrounded by flesh then that
will counteract it. And the other point that we that we spoke
about yesterday was that the משנה Mishna, introduced, it sounded like a
new concept of a טריפה, treifah, which is that if the hind
leg is broken high enough up it makes the animal טריפה, treifah,
and it was hard for us to understand why, and that was
a whole new case that was not mentioned in אלו טריפות, eilu
treifos, and we just mentioned yesterday that it is worth noting that
the משנה Mishna doesn't use the phrase טריפה, treifah just uses the
phrase פסולה, psulah, but the גמרא Gemara chooses to see it as
a טריפה because it's concerned. David, you had a question? Alright, I
am just trying to, unfortunately... רש"י Rashi does like an amazing job
on this, you know, without רש"י's Rashi, extensive commentaries on this page.
Well even with רש"י's Rashi extensive commentaries on this page I have
to tell you that I was, I needed to use the picture
book on some of this part. Obviously they didn't have the picture
book back then but he sort of like tries to provide a...
well right, what makes you say that more than any other place?
Just because here you feel it more because of the lack of
graphics and images? Right, I also have to tell you that reading
רש"י, Rashi. I would have liked it if רש"י Rashi would have
drawn a picture or two. Back in ancient times, so it's just
wondered, did they actually take the students to the slaughterhouse to show
what the different body parts were? I mean there are stories that
the ראב"ד, Ravyad, I don't know if all were, there are stories
that the ראב"ד Ravyad would bring in animal parts to show his
students. I think that it had to do a lot, maybe a
lot with
the, what do you call it, with the culture. I have a
sense that it happened more in ספרד Sfarad than it did in
אשכנז Ashkenaz actually. Da Vinci was studying corpses you know, yeah, but
that was a little bit after, a bit, but still under
these conditions and he says dangling... oh with these conditions if the...
yeah you can eat the dangling limb if it is... right, right,
okay. Alright, let's continue now hopefully finding exactly now to the next
משנה. Mishnah, השוחט את הבהמה, Hashochet es habeheimah, so we are away
from the dangling limb thankfully and now we are going on, last
משנה Mishnah of the פרק. What? You slaughter an animal, ומצא בה
שליא, matza bo shilyah, and you find in it a placenta. Right,
the placenta is not the amniotic sac, right? The placenta is the
part that feeds the fetus, right? Okay fine, you find in it
the placenta. They were putting it in here the amniotic sac? What?
Not calling it the placenta, they're calling it the amniotic sac.
And but there are two things, right? There's the amniotic sac where
the fetus is, right? And then there's the placenta which surrounds it
and feeds it, right? Okay so this is the placenta.
You find it without the baby. What?
Just the placenta, no fetus. And the question is what happened to
the fetus?
Surprised they didn't put this right after the fetus. What do they
have it, the whole?
I don't know because we were still discussing the limbs. I don't
know exactly what the order is. Yeah, I don't know. Okay, alright,
moving
on. Alright, השוחט את הבהמה ומצא בה שליא, Hashochet es habeheimah umatzabo
shilyah, you find in it this placenta. So now we know that
if you find in it a fetus, unless it's a nine-month-old live
fetus where there's a debate of רבי מאיר Reb Meir and the
Sages, but if it's a dead fetus or if it's not nine
months old, we know that it's made permissible with the שחיטה shechitah
of the mother, so there's like no question that if you find
in the placenta it's going to be made permissible. So now you
technically you can eat it, but the משנה sort of voices it's
a little bit of its... said it's a feel it's gross. So
it says
נפש היפה תאכלנה. nefesh hayafa tochalennah. So the the nice soul, which
is like a euphemism, the meaning the non-finicky person can eat that
if you want to eat it געזונטערהייט. gezunterheit. It's technically kosher.
Okay, it reminds me of those reality TV shows.
Right, okay, are they?
Yes they were.
They were discussing
they didn't do it.
Alright, really? Exactly this? Eating a placenta? Oh my god. ואינו מטמא
לא טומאת אוכלין ולא טומאת נבילות. ve'eino mitamei lo tumas ochlin velo
tumas nevelos. Since normal people don't eat it, it is, it does
not cause טומאה tumah of foodstuff. So if something טמא tamei touches
it, it will not become טמא tamei because it is not normally
eaten and you have to be food and normally eaten to become
טמא. tamei. And it does not cause the טומאה tumah of a
נבילה nevelah if the animal was not שחט shechted and died, the
animal... the meat of the animal, the carcass of the animal is
a נבילה, neveilah, but not this, because this is not meat. Okay,
so even it's a placenta, it's not meat, and the only part
if a bone of a dead animal does not cause the טומאה
tumah of נבילה, neveilah, the teeth do not, so the placenta does
not. So if the animal naturally died, this is not a נבילה.
neveilah.
Especially while it was here, right, for the טומאה? tumah?
No, I think it was because we're talking about fetuses. I mean,
we're talking about and eating them, and their טומאה. tumah. This is
an exact except now we're moving from fetuses to placentas. Okay. חשב
עליו, chishav alav, עליה, aleha, if you planned on eating it, as
we said in the beginning of the משנה, some people might choose
to eat
it, מטמא טומאת אוכלין אבל לא טומאת נבילה. metamei tumas ochlin aval
lo tumas neveilah. Then it can become food if you decide that
you're going to eat it, then you've made it into food, but
it will never become a נבילה neveilah because to be a נבילה
neveilah it's not enough to be food, it has to be meat,
and this isn't meat, it's just a
placenta. Okay. שליה שיצתה מקצתה אסורה באכילה. shilya sheyatza miktzasa asurah beachilah.
Now, the animal is part of the placenta has come out of
the animal's womb, this is like the limb coming out of the
by with the fetus, and then you שחט shecht the mother. What
is the status of that placenta? When it was in the womb,
you could eat it. Now that part has emerged, what's the story?
So it says you can't eat it. Why not? Because the basic
point is, if there's a placenta, then there definitely was a fetus
at one time. So where is that fetus? So who knows? It's
probably been, you know, it got aborted in the womb and it
was, you know, miscarried, and it's the remnants are some of the
gook that's in that's that's coming out. So the concern is is
that when this placenta is coming out, maybe some of maybe some
of the dissolved fetus is coming out with
it. And therefore, that's okay, but you might might assume reasonably that
if it's dissolved or whatever it no longer has the status of
a fetus. You know, interestingly, that's not the assumption here. The assumption
is is that if you do have the contents of the dissolved
fetus, it's like this fetus was birthed. And therefore, if it's like
this fetus was birthed, right, so therefore it is forbidden because then
it was somehow like a dead Imagine that it was not some
dissolved stuff. Imagine that it was actually a stillbirth. Okay, so what
would have happened if like, you know, a stillbirth animal had come
out? Then once the head had emerged, it was considered born. Once
it's born it requires שחיטה, shechitah but you can't do שחיטה shechitah,
because it's already dead, here you can't do שחיטה shechitah because it's
dissolved. So therefore you can't eat it. So the same is true
in this case, when a part of the fetus emerged, a part
of the stillbirth, a part of the what do you call it?
Placenta emerges, we're concerned that the dissolved head of the fetus has
come out with it, and that's some of the gook that's around
it, and therefore, and it's all attached to the to the placenta,
and therefore, you can't eat it's like it was born and therefore
requires שחיטה, shechitah obviously שחיטה Shechita. isn't relevant, and therefore you can't
eat it.
What about the part that's inside?
Both parts, it doesn't matter. Let's say the head of a fetus
had emerged, right? That would be considered like it was born. So
even when you שחט shecht the mother, that was like the first
משנה, once the head of the fetus has emerged, you can't eat
the part that's inside, you can't eat the whole fetus. Now normally,
if the fetus were alive and the head had emerged, fine, it's
born, now שחט shecht it and eat it. But if the fetus
emerged dead with the head coming out, you can't eat any part
of it. So this is sort of conceptually like a dead fetus
emerging. Although it is strange, because you would have said, that's one
thing if it's like formed and it's meat and it's whatever, I
could say it's a dead fetus, it's a נבילה, neveilah, I can't
do שחיטה on it, it's an animal and so on. But here
why not just say it's like, you know, garbage, and there's no
הלכה halachah about about the discharges of an animal. So,
right? I mean if you consider like let's say an animal, you
know, let's say it was I mean, again, like try to think
of some case that's not too gross, but it'll be gross, but
okay. Let's say, let's say, let's say mucus came out of an
animal. You wouldn't say, oh, it's forbidden, you know, whatever, right? It's
it's just some discharge of an animal. So what makes it So
the fact that even it's interesting that even in its dissolved state,
it's being given that status of an animal once it's come out
of the womb and therefore cannot be eaten. You Charlie, you had
a question? Okay. All right, so
that is סימן ולד באשה וסימן ולד בבהמה. siman vlad beishah vesiman
vlad bebehemah. The emerging of the of the
placenta is a sign of birth for a woman and a sign
of birth for an animal. So again, when there's no fetus, we
have to be concerned that the emerging of the placenta indicates that
the dissolved fetus is coming out as well. So in this case
also it means you can't eat the placenta, but for let's say
a human woman, it would also mean when she has טומאת לידה,
tumat leidah, when she's considered to be טמאה tamei as a result
of childbirth, okay, so there it's also when she gives birth even
even when she miscarries, she has טומאת לידה, tumat leidah, and what
is that moment when that occurs, when if you don't have an
actual fetus coming out, when the placenta comes out.
Artscroll is using amniotic sac as opposed to placenta.
Yeah, they never use the word placenta.
That is very interesting. You know, I wonder how they how they
translate the word No, שפיר, shfiyir, because שפיר shfiyir is what normally
means amniotic sac, that comes up on the next עמוד. amud. Can
I see your Rabbi Artscroll for a minute? Artscroll's not תורה מסיני.
Torah MiSinai. Exactly.
This has
actually a long comment.
They have a long comment.
The normal translation of שליא Shilya is placenta and שפיר Shefir is
amniotic sac. שליא, Shilya, I would say, in regular, you know,
I always thought of it as a placenta also.
It translates
שפיר Shefir as
embryo.
שפיר Shefir
is embryo?
That's what they translate
it as.
Yeah, I see that's what they're translating שפיר Shefir as, as embryo.
It was my understanding that שפיר Shefir was
the embryonic sac, or what do you call it, amniotic sac, and
the שליא Shilya is actually the placenta.
So according to them, what? Does anybody know what's in
modern Hebrew?
What's that in modern Hebrew?
I have no
idea.
One minute. Oh yeah, what does Steinsaltz say?
One minute. It doesn't really, he does not translate it.
He
says דינא דפירוש בלבד Dina
de-perush bilvad
like the regular perush.
Well,
you
certainly understand why if it does mean the amniotic sac, you would
understand more why when it emerges you're concerned about the emergence of
the actual dissolved embryo. I mean, that I was aware of as
I was working through this, which is the sense that when the
sac comes out, you're afraid that the dissolved head is coming out
with it, makes a lot more sense if it's the content of
a
sac rather than right, rather than the placenta and maybe it just
happens to be wrapped in with it. I'll have to check it
up because the question is what שפיר Shefir means. They translate שפיר
Shefir as the embryo itself. And I've assumed that שפיר Shefir meant
the sac and the שליא Shilya was the placenta. So I'll have
to check it in.
Yeah, it says in on עמוד Amud. א', השליא היא גוש גדול
מלא
כלי דם הצמוד
לדופן הרחם.
Ha-shilya hi gush gadol male kley
dam ha-tsamud le-dofen ha-rechem.
Okay. כאשר העובר נרחץ ממנו בתוכה. Ka'asher ha-ubar nirchats mimeno betocha. בתוכה.
Betocha. So that would be amniotic sac. So he does say, and
what does he say
the שפיר Shefir or the שליא Shilya is?
It's the שליא. Shilya.
What
does he say the שפיר Shefir is?
He
doesn't say. He just has one thing here about שליא. Shilya.
שפיר Shefir is on the next page, on
the next
עמוד.
No, שפיר Shefir is earlier.
No.
שליא, Shilya, how would you...
שליא. Shilya. That's according to whom?
To Google. Rabbi Google.
Very big Google. Placenta.
Yes,
well that I know, but the question is what it means in
the גמרא. Gemara. All right. I think we just don't have good
enough internet up here. All right, anyway, we will have to, I
will have to get back to you on that. It does, I
have to say that as I...
what? He said here, מציאותה של שליא Metsi'utah shel shilya וסימן מובהק
לכך
שיש
לאישה או בבהמה הריון
ve-siman muvhak lekach she-yesh la-isha
o bi-behema herayon שלא נשלם
כראוי.
she-lo
nishlam kera'uy.
Right, that we know, that's a סימן ולד באישה, Siman vlad be-isha,
סימן ולד בבהמה. siman vlad be-behema. But it could be the placenta
or the amniotic sac. All right, I will tell you, I will
tell you that as I was, you know, that this סוגיא sugya
makes more sense, I will grant that, makes more sense assuming that
the שליא Shilya means the amniotic sac. The whole assumption that the
animal is coming out with, the dissolved embryo is coming out with
it, does make more sense in terms of a sac. I'm going
to have to check that because it was always clear, it was
always clear to me that the שפיר Shefir meant was like more
of connected to the actual fetus itself, and the classic translations that
I've seen have had שפיר Shefir as the sac and the שליא
Shilya as the placenta. But this is interesting suggesting that the שפיר
Shefir means the embryo itself.
What's the...
the placenta. No, but the שפיר Shefir always is something closer to
the fetus itself. Of course, what Artscroll did is it said the
שפיר Shefir means the fetus itself, which is a little funny because
earlier the fetus was referred to as עובר, Ubar, but maybe that
was when it was more viable and here when it's dissolved. So
I don't know. I will have to get back to you on
that. Okay, so let's keep on going. The משנה says like
this. Okay, המבכרת שהפילה שליא, Ha-mevakeret she-hipila shilya, ישליכנה לכלבים. Yashlichena la-klavim.
If an animal that is giving birth to a firstborn, meaning has
yet to have its
firstborn, and instead of giving birth to a live firstborn, it just,
you know, gives birth to a שליא. Shilya. to this, what do
you call it, to this either placenta or embryonic sac, okay, so
maybe it's the firstborn, maybe it's not, that's dissolved in it.
So
what is the הלכה? Halacha? Remember, as you might remember from before,
the firstborn does not have to be viable. So the הלכה Halacha
is ישליכנה לכלבים, Yashlichena lachlavim, you can just give it to the
dogs. Why is that? Why aren't we concerned that this is a
dissolved firstborn and so on? So the גמרא Gemara will say, well
not every firstborn child has a status of a בכור, Bechor, it
has to be a firstborn male. Okay, but it's still 50-50. So
the גמרא Gemara will say there are some firstborns that even if
they're males don't have the status of a בכור. Bechor. We'll see
that when we get to the גמרא. Gemara. So it's a little
less than 50% that this has קדושה Kedusha of a בכור. Bechor.
And since it's a little less than 50%, that's a little surprising
that you would say okay but who cares even if it's only
49% isn't that enough to be strict? But nevertheless the משנה says
that since the majority of things that come out will not be
a בכור Bechor and this is dissolved and you don't know what
it was, you don't have to assume it's a בכור Bechor and
you can give it to the dogs.
The next one is definitely not a בכור.
Bechor. But this one it might have been a female and even
if it's a male not all males are בכורות, Bechorot, some rare
cases, we'll talk about them in the גמרא. Gemara. So therefore since
it's less than 50% a בכור, Bechor, this dissolved thing just give
it to the dogs. ובמקדשים Uvimukdashim but if it was the you
know this thing was discharged from a sanctified animal, then תקבר, Tikaver,
then it has the sanctity of a קורבן Korban because something born
from a female cow or sheep that was a sacrifice also has
the sanctity of a sacrifice whether it's male or female. So therefore
since whatever this is, even though it's dissolved, would have had that
sanctity, you have to bury it because it retains the sanctity.
And that's a very interesting thing, it was like you know let's
say it just defecated,
you'd have to bury that? No, no, no, so that's the thing.
We're treating this that's similar to the beginning of this משנה, that
even though the beginning of the משנה says it's not meat and
it's not a נבלה, Neveila, we are treating it as an actual
as though it were a stillbirth. It might not be meat but
it's still somehow the birth of the thing. And I understand, so
it's not because it's a discharge, it's because it's a birth. Which
is why we say that when it comes out you can't eat
it and why we say that when it comes out and it's
from a קורבן Korban it has the קדושה Kedusha and when it's
all these things only because we're treating it as a birth. What?
It has an הנאה מגללים של בהמת הקדש? Hana'ah miglalim shel behemat
hekdesh? Yes.
Okay. ואין קוברים אותה בפרשת דרכים. Ve'ein kovrim otah beparashat drachim. Now
apparently what they used to do when there were these sort of
aborted fetuses of animals is that they would bury them by the
crossroads as some type of a you know magic or something. So
isn't that אסור Assur to do?
Well that's why you can't.
You cannot bury it at the crossroads, ואין תולין אותה באילן, Ve'ein
tolin otah be'ilan, you can't suspend it from a tree. These are
things done to I don't know protect against evil spirits or something.
מפני דרכי האמורי Mipnei darchei Ha'emori because of the ways of the
Amorites which is based on the פסוק, Pasuk, you know it says
ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו Uvechukoteihem lo telechu don't go in their paths. It's
interesting the use of the phrase אמורי. Emori. They weren't really, sometimes
the גמרא Gemara does use that to refer to like non-Jews, but
anyway presumably that's evoking the biblical reference to the people of the
land of כנען. Kna'an. Okay so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. What?
It's not kind of obvious?
Well let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about it and it'll
be less obvious. Okay. מנא הני מילי? Mena hani milei? Where is
this from? דתנו רבנן Detanu rabanan we taught: כל בהמה תאכלו Kol
behema tochlu you could eat all animals, meaning it's meant to mean
anything in an animal. לרבות את השליה Lerabot et hashilya even the
שליה Shilya inside of an animal which should be pretty obvious if
you could eat the fetus you'd all the more so be able
to eat the שליה. Shilya. But anyway, יכול אפילו יצאה מקצתה Yachol
afillu yatz'ah miktzatah maybe even if part of it
emerged? תלמוד לומר אותה Talmud lomar otah "it". אותה ולא שלייתה. Otah
velo shilyatah. Only it when it is the animal itself but not
its שליה. Shilya. Again whichever part that means. So what does it
mean? I mean you just said you could eat the שליה. Shilya.
It means once the שליה Shilya emerged then you can't eat it
for the reasons we said because it might have the dissolved fetus
attached to it. מכדי, let's take a look, אין שליה בלא ולד.
Ein shilya belo velad. There's no שליה Shilya without a fetus. If
there's a שליה Shilya there's definitely a fetus. למה לי קרא? Lama
li kra? Why do I need the verse? Of course once the
שליה Shilya comes out I have to assume that there's a fetus
with it and that you can't eat. So קרא אסמכתא בעלמא. Kra
asmachta be'alma. Yeah the verse is only you know is only a
biblical connection and we really could have figured it out even without
the verse. Which is again funny because even assuming the שליה Shilya
is the embryonic sac and that obviously therefore you're concerned that the
fetus is inside of it, right? It's not so clear to me
that you would assume that a dissolved fetus has any status and
should be a problem when it emerges from the womb, right? A
stillbirth is one thing. If you have a dead stillborn calf you
won't eat it once it emerges from the womb. It requires שחיטה.
But if you just have dissolved stuff in a sac, right? Even
if there was a ולד Valad at one time, now if it's
dissolved I would still think you'd need a verse to tell me
that that is a problem. So it's interesting the גמרא Gemara says
that we could have figured all of that out ourselves. Okay let's
go
on. ואינה מטמאה Ve'eina metama it does not cause טומאה Tuma because
it's not foodstuff and it's not
meat. בעי רבי יצחק בר נפקא? Ba'ei Rabbi Yitzchak bar Nafcha? Rabbi
Yitzchak bar Nafcha asked. עור חמור ששלקו מהו? Or chamor sheshalko mahu?
What is the status of the skin of a donkey that was
boiled and made perhaps somewhat
quasi-edible? Is it considered
like the meat itself? So למאי, lemai, what's the question about? אי
לטומאת אוכלין תנינא, ei letumat ochlin tanina, if whether it's considered food
and can now
become טמא tamei as food, we've taught that. אי לטומאת נבילות, ei
letumat nevelot, if whether it's considered actually to be the meat of
the carcass itself and cause טומאה tumah of a נבילה, neveila, so
תנינא tanina we also taught that. טומאת אוכלין, tumat ochlin, where do
we see about the
טומאת tumat foodstuff? דתניא, detanya, we taught in the
ברייתא. Baraita. העור והשליה אין מטמאין טומאת אוכלין, Ha'or vehashilya ein mitammin
tumat ochlin, the skin of an animal
and the fetus or the placenta
do not cause the טומאה tumah of foodstuff because they're not normally
edible. עור ששלקו, or sheshalko, if however you boiled the
skin, והשליה שחישב עליה, vehashilya shechishav aleha, and you planned on eating
the שליה, shilya, which is the words of our משנה, you planned
on eating the שליה, shilya, then it says
מטמאין טומאת אוכלין. mitammin tumat ochlin. So if you're a weird person
and you are going to eat the skin after boiling it or
you're a weird person and you're going to actually eat this שליה,
shilya, whatever it is, the sac or this placenta or whatever, then
you've made it into food and it can become טמא tamei if
it touches something טמא tamei as food. So that's explicit there that
if you cook it it can become
טמא. tamei. One second. טומאת נבילות נמי תנינא, tumat nevelot nami tanina,
as far as it being considered a נבילה neveila itself, that we've
also taught. בנבילתה, benevelatah, it says if you touch the carcass of
a dead
animal, ולא בעורה, velo be'orah, not if you touch the skin, ולא
בעצמות, velo be'atzamot, or the bones, ולא בגידים, velo begidim, not the
sinews, ולא בקרניים, velo bekarnayim, and not the horns, ולא בטלפיים, velo
betalafayim, or the hooves. Only if you touch the actual flesh. And
this isn't the flesh, it's the skin. So what's your question? We
know that it's not a נבילה, neveila, we know that it's not
the
flesh, and as far as a food we know that if you
cook it and plan on eating it, you will make it into
food and otherwise not. So what's your question about the skin of
a donkey? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, ve'amar Raba Bar Bar Chana,
לא נצרכה אלא שעשאן סיקאי דסאטרא, lo nitzrecha ela she'asahan sika'e desatara,
and this point that the skin does not consider to be like
the flesh, we said explicitly even if you've made them like a
type of a cooked in a pot with various types of spices
and tried to make it edible, it still doesn't turn it into
flesh and it doesn't cause the טומאה tumah of a נבילה. neveila.
So food it could be if you process it that way and
plan on doing it that way, נבילה neveila and flesh it will
never be. So what's your
question? לעולם לטומאת אוכלין. lo'olam letumat ochlin. No, the question is can
it become טמא tamei like food? So haven't we already taught that?
No, ושאני עור חמור דמאיס. v'shani or chamor dema'is. Even if other
skins, like the skin of a cow maybe if you cook it
and make it enough spices, I don't know, you can make it
somewhat edible and that could be considered food, maybe the skin of
a donkey will never be considered food because it's too repulsive. So
having never eaten the skin of a cow or the skin of
a donkey I can't tell you, okay, but anyway, but it is
interesting because it gets into the question of subjective definition versus objective
limits. Right, our משנה says if you plan on eating this שליה
shilya then you've made it into food, but that's because some weird
people will do that. But if
nobody, almost nobody would ever do this type of a thing, then
even if you're planning on eating it, even that, even your subjective
definition is not going to be enough if it's too much of,
like, what do they call it, too tail? Yeah, what are those
things in probability, distribution, two standard deviations removed from the norm?
Then your subjective definition is not going to be meaningful, and that
would be the question here about the skin of a donkey. Yes.
What if you're using it as medicine over here?
That might be, but it doesn't make it food. Only food becomes
טמא. tamei.
Yeah,
could be a salve, could be other things, but it won't become
טמא tamei as a food. Yeah.
Strange that you said non-kosher animals interfere here?
Yeah, because you mean because can non-kosher things become טמא tamei altogether?
Yeah. Well, first of all, it's a very important question about the
skin because this actually gets to the whole issue of, well, that's
right, but yeah, first of all, that's right. One question about non-kosher
food: is it food to become טמא? tamei? And I believe the
answer to that is yes, even though right you're not allowed to
eat it, since it's edible. The other question though, interestingly, is the
same way this is not considered a נבילה neveila because it's not
flesh, it's actually also things that are not actually
not technically forbidden even in terms of כשרות. kashrus. For example, this
is the whole issue in terms of gelatin, which is made from
pig bones, right? So some of the argument is that they're so
dried out and processed or whatever that they don't really retain their
original status. But some would say that even if you didn't go
through that whole thing, the only the actual flesh of the pig
is forbidden and not the bones. Now the question about bones with
marrow and bones without marrow because the marrow is like the flesh
and so on, it also raises interesting... questions it's a little bizarre
because we've been teaching that things that come from a non-כשר kosher
animal, like milk from a non-כשר kosher animal, right, are not כשר.
kosher. So how are the actual bones of the non-כשר kosher animal
itself? But yeah, there actually is some question about that, about that
the, that the actual, if it's not the flesh, might actually not
even be not כשר. kosher. So what about the case of gelatin
then?
Well, that's not today's שיעור.
shiur. But anyway, I just mentioned it for interesting color. But anyway,
but, but yeah, I think the fact that it is physically edible
or barring religious restrictions is still enough in terms of טומאת אוכלין.
tumas ochlin. Okay, so let's now continue. I want to make sure
we finish this
today. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Eleazar, שליה שיצאה, shilya sheyatza, part
of it emerged, then it's like it was born, you can't eat
it. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Eleazar, לא שנו אלא שאין עמה
ולד. lo shanu ela she'ein imah vlad. When is it that you
have to be concerned that it was born, that there was a
fetus there, when there's no actual present fetus? Okay. אבל יש עמה
ולד, aval yesh imah vlad, if there is a present
fetus, אין חוששין לולד אחר. ein chosheshin levlad acher. So let's say
this שליה, shilya, again, whether it's the sac or the placenta, emerges,
and there still is a fetus that's up there in the womb
that you see that hasn't come out yet. Do we have to
say, oh, so that one fetus, but maybe this
שליה shilya has a different dissolved fetus with it? And therefore, maybe
I can't eat the שליה shilya because even though there's another fetus
up there, there was a dissolved fetus with this one and I
can't eat that? You're not concerned about. If you have one ולד
vlad and one שליה, shilya, you assume they go together. Okay? And
you're not concerned that there's some other dissolved fetus going on. And
then you can eat the שליה. shilya. Right. And then you can
eat the שליה, shilya, because then you see where
the ולד vlad is. Exactly. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, בין אין עמה ולד בין יש עמה
ולד, bein ein imah vlad bein yesh imah vlad, whether it doesn't
have a fetus or not a fetus, חוששין לולד אחר. chosheshin levlad
acher. You are concerned that there is another dissolved fetus. And now
I should say that this also would argue for the idea of
שליה shilya being the embryonic sac. Because, because if it's just the
placenta, of course, it's like it's patently obvious, of course the placenta
isn't combined with the fetus. So if you see a fetus, you
see a placenta, why should there be anything else? But if it's
the embryonic sac, then the point could be, okay, there's a fetus,
but it should have been inside of the embryonic sac. So maybe
even if there is a fetus, I could be concerned that there's
something else inside of this embryonic sac, yet another fetus. Okay. So
that is what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. Okay. איני, eini, is this really true?
ואמר רבי ירמיה לחומרא אמר רבי אלעזר. ve'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah l'chumra amar
Rabbi Eleazar. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah says that this statement of רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Eleazar, that it's only when there is a fetus, it's
only when there's no fetus, was said to be strict. But the
way we framed it, he's being lenient. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
even with another fetus, you have to be concerned that there's a
dissolved fetus with this שליה, shilya, and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar says
you don't have to be concerned. But we, we have a tradition
that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar was being strict here. אלא אי אתמר
הכי אתמר, ella i itmar hachi itmar, if it was said, here's
how it was said. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Eleazar, רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Eleazar says, לא שנו, lo shanu, when is it that we
assume, that we are concerned that there's a fetus with this שליה,
shilya, אלא שאינה קשורה בולד. ella she'eina kshura bevlad. Whether there is
a fetus or not a fetus, we'll be concerned that there's, that
there's a dissolved fetus with this שליה. shilya. The exception will be
if the fetus is intertwined with this שליה. shilya. This shows
קשורה, kshura, it's like intertwined with it. Or, I'm sorry. When it's
not intertwined, when it's even if there's a fetus present, when it's
not intertwined with this שליה, shilya, we'll always assume that there might
be another, another dissolved fetus. אבל, aval, however, קשורה בולד, kshura bevlad,
if the שליה shilya is intertwined, literally tied, tied to the ולד,
vlad, אין חוששין לולד אחר. ein chosheshin levlad acher. Then there's no
question that they go together. So according to this, רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Eleazar saying if it's literally intertwined or then there's no question that
they go together, but under all other circumstances, even with a fetus,
you'll be concerned that there's yet another dissolved fetus with this שליה.
shilya. That's what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar says. So that's pretty strict,
that the only exception he makes is when they're intertwined. רבי יוחנן
אומר, Rabbi Yochanan omer, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, אנו אין
לנו אלא שליה בלא ולד. anu ein lanu ella shilya belo vlad.
אנו אין לנו אלא שליה בלא ולד. anu ein lanu ella shilya
belo vlad. The only time we're concerned is if there's no fetus.
אבל יש עמה ולד, aval yesh imah vlad, if there is a
fetus, בין קשורה בולד בין אינה קשורה בולד, bein kshura bevlad bein
eina kshura bevlad, whether, whether the שליה shilya is intertwined with the
fetus or not, אין חוששין לולד אחר. ein chosheshin levlad acher. We
are not concerned with another, with another, with another fetus. So here
the point is, you have this שליה, shilya, again, here I'll concede
that it makes a lot more sense assuming it's the embryonic sac,
because then there's still the problem, the reason that makes us concerned,
suspicious, is that the fetus is not inside of the sac, it's
separate from it. So therefore, the only, the only exception רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Eleazar would make is if it's intertwined. Then of course I'll
assume they go together. But if they're not intertwined, I have to
be concerned that there's yet another dissolved fetus when the שליה shilya
is separate. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says as long as there's
a fetus there, you assume the שליה shilya goes with it. You
don't have to assume something, that there's yet another fetus going, dissolved
fetus. present here. והיינו דאמר רבי ירמיה *V'hainu d'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah* and
that's what Rabbi Yirmiyah says לחומרא אמר רבי אליעזר *l'chumra amar Rabbi
Eliezer*. Rabbi Eliezer is being even stricter. The only case he'll exclude
is when it's intertwined with the fetus itself. Otherwise he's concerned that
there is yet another dissolved fetus going on here. תניא כוותיה דרבי
אליעזר *Tanya k'vatei d'Rabbi Eliezer*. We taught like Rabbi Eliezer that most
of the time we'll be concerned with a dissolved fetus. המפלת מין
בהמה חיה ועוף *Hamapelet min behema chaya v'of*. If a woman miscarriages
and the fetus looks like some type of an animal, חיה ועוף
*chaya v'of*. Okay, it's very deformed. Now is will that make her
טמאה לידה *tmei'ah leida*? Is it a fetus? The חכמים *Chachamim* say
it does not. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says that it does. רש"י
Rashi, *Rashi* says we're going here like the חכמים *Chachamim*. So she
has this miscarriage, fetus is deformed, it doesn't look human. Whether the
חז"ל *Chazal* really thought that it was something other than human or
just thought it was deformed is not clear, but whatever, it doesn't
look human so therefore it does not make her טמאה לידה *tmei'ah
leida*.
You say it looks like, it doesn't say.
I know, I know, which is why you are correct. A type
of a בהמה *behema*, which is why cause look it really actually,
I know, I was sort of trying to finesse that one because
that's okay. I appreciate, I appreciate your attention to those details. No,
because look, if even a total miscarriage that is dissolved right like
a שליא *shilya* or whatever makes her טמאה לידה *tmei'ah leida*, you
would think what difference does it make if the fetus is deformed?
The only logic to exclude this case is if you actually think
that it's not even human altogether, not just deformed. So yeah, you
are correct. Anyway, so she's not going to be טמאה לידה *tmei'ah
leida* as a result of that. ושליא עמהן *V'shilya imahen*. However, there
is a שליא *shilya* again, either placenta or embryonic sac. So the
question is she's not going to be טמאה לידה *tmei'ah leida* because
of this thing that looks like an animal or whatever bird, but
maybe the שליא *shilya* indicates that there's yet another fetus that's dissolved
and that should make her טמאה לידה *tmei'ah leida*. So what is
the story? בזמן שקשורה בהן *Bizman shekshura bahen*, if it's tied to
them, אין חוששין לולד אחר *ein chosheshin l'valad acher*. You don't have
to be concerned about anything else and therefore she is not טמאה
לידה *tmei'ah leida* because all you had was this one bizarre bird.
And this is like Rabbi Eliezer, that the key is whether it
is wrapped up with the שליא *shilya* or not. אינה
קשורה בהן *Eina kshura bahen*, if this deformed fetus is not wrapped
up with the שליא *shilya*, then maybe the שליא *shilya* represents another
ולד *vlad* and therefore maybe she is טמאה לידה *tmei'ah leida*. הריני
מטיל עליה חומר שני ולדות *Hareini matil aleha chomer shnei vladot*. I
apply to her the stringency of two births. שאני אומר *She'ani omer*
שמא נימוח שפיר של שליא *shema nimoch shapir shel shilya*, maybe the
שפיר *shapir* of the שליא *shilya* dissolved, which now ArtScroll translates as
maybe the embryo of the שפיר *shapir* of the שליא *shilya* dissolved.
I thought it meant maybe the embryonic sac. But okay. ושמא נימוחה
שליא יתרה של שפיר *V'shema nimucha shilya yatera shel shapir*. And maybe
right, how is it that you just have one שליא *shilya* and
one fetus if they don't go together? Well, the way you have
one of each if they don't go together is the counterpart of
each one got dissolved. Right, so the counterpart of the fetus, the
sac and the placenta, that got dissolved, and the counterpart of the
placenta and the sac, the fetus got dissolved, or and you're left
with one of each, but maybe they don't really match. Maybe they're
really from different fetuses, from different births. And therefore even though you
have a fetus and the שליא *shilya*, says this משנה *Mishnah*, if
they're not intertwined, you have to concern yourself that there are maybe
two births. So even though the woman is not טמאה *tmei'ah* because
of this you know deformed fetus, she would be טמאה *tmei'ah* because
the שליא *shilya* might indicate yet another birth. What does it mean
the stringency of two births? Because whenever a woman gives birth, there's
a stringency and a leniency. The stringency is she's טמאה *tmei'ah* for
a week or two depending on male or female, but the leniency
is that if she bleeds after that week or two, it does
not make her טמאה *tmei'ah* for the next either 33 or 66
days depending on male or female. But because here you can't tell,
maybe she didn't give birth, right? Maybe all she had was this
deformed thing which does not make her טמאה *tmei'ah*. So she has
both stringencies. On the worst end of the on the she's immediately
טמאה *tmei'ah* for two weeks because maybe this שליא *shilya* represents a
female that is dissolved and that makes her טמאה *tmei'ah* for two
weeks. And on the other hand, if she bleeds later she's טמאה
*tmei'ah* because maybe there's been no birth here and therefore any further
bleeding will make her טמאה *tmei'ah*. That's what it means the stringencies
of both births. Okay, so here you have this question that even
if there is a fetus, maybe if it's not intertwined with the
שליא *shilya*, there really is yet another birth going on here and
the counterparts have been dissolved and we have to be concerned. Okay,
so that is the question and again I will concede that this
certainly makes it sound that the שליא *shilya* is the embryonic sac,
not the placenta. So I will have to research it in other
cases and see if that's definitely the case. Okay, let's now do
the last case of the משנה *Mishnah*, or the second to last
case, המבכרת שהפילה *Hamivakeret shehipila*, an animal that has never given birth
that now miscarried, basically what comes later will not be a בכור
*bechor* because the בכור *bechor* doesn't have to be viable and this
thing itself doesn't have the קדושה *kedusha* of a בכור *bechor*. and
you give it to the dogs. Now why not? If we've been
assuming that even when this thing comes out, we treat it like
a dissolved birth, and we treat it like a בכור *bechor*, why
doesn't it have the sanctity of a בכור *bechor*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says: מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? What's the reason? אמר רב
איקא בריה דרב אמי *Amar Rav Ika brei d'Rav Ami*: רוב בהמות
יולדות סבר הקדוש בבכורה ומיעוט בהמה דבר שאינו קדוש בבכורה *rov behemot
yoldot sabar hakadosh bivchora u'mi'ut behema davar she'eino kadosh bivchora*. Most animals,
even when they give birth to male animals, most of the time
it's something that will have the sanctity of a בכור *bechor*, but
there are times where it won't have the sanctity of a בכור
*bechor*. What are those times? Even as a male it won't have
the sanctity of the בכור *bechor*. ומאי ניהו *u'mai ni'u*? What is
it? נדמה *nidmeh*. Something that is looks like, meaning that it is
a... it's similar to the case we have before by the female
woman, that you have a sheep that gives birth to something that
looks like a calf, or a cow that gives birth to something
that looks like a sheep. In those cases, it is... does not
have the קדושה *kedusha* of a בכור *bechor* because it does not
look like the right species. It's very... look at רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*
here, three lines down in the wide lines, נדמה *nidmeh*. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says, can anybody see what word that is? Where is this?
Three lines down in the wide lines. Give me the words. נדמה
*nidmeh*.
Counterfeit. Counterfeita, right?
Counterfeit. רחל שילדה מין עז או עז שילדה דומה לרחל *rachel she'yalda
min ez o ez she'yalda domeh l'rachel*. Okay?
If a sheep gives birth to something that looks like a goat,
or a goat gives birth to something that looks like a sheep.
Okay, so that does not have the קדושה *kedusha* of a בכור
*bechor* because it looks different. He doesn't actually claim that it is
a different species, but it looks different. Let's just finish this point.
So therefore, sometimes even as a male, there's a small percentage of
cases it would not have the קדושה *kedusha* of a בכור *bechor*.
וכל היולדות יולדות מחצה זכר מחצה נקבות *v'chol hayoldot yoldot mechtza zachar
mechtza nekevot*. And we know that animals and humans, whatever, it's 50%
male, 50% females. סמוך מיעוטא דנדמה למחצה דנקבות *smoch mi'uta d'nidmeh l'mechtza
d'nekevot*, so you add the tiny percentage of those that are נדמה
*nidmeh* to the percentage that are females, and you'll find והוו להו
זכר מיעוטא *v'havu lehu zachar mi'uta*. The males that are קדוש בבכורה
*kadosh bivchora* only like 49.9%, right? Because 50% are female and of
the 50% that are males, 0.1% is not קדוש בבכורה *kadosh bivchora*.
So there's a tiny percent less than 50%, so you can go
by רוב *rov* and you don't have to treat it with the
קדושה *kedusha* of בכור *bechor*, which I have to admit is like
pretty amazing. First of all, that that tiny bit less that makes
that side is enough to be significant. And number two, that, you
know, okay, you know, normally... you would have normally expected that something
like this which is דאורייתא *d'oraita*, the sanctity of a בכור *bechor*,
might as well just be safe, play it safe. So it's a
pretty profound statement of going by רוב *rov* when you cannot resolve
it anywhere... anywhere else. Because obviously there's no other way to resolve
it here, you know, other than to determine any more facts, so
that you can completely go by the רוב *rov*. Yes.
Two questions on that. One is the... then for sure then given
like the one that's like the Koy's case of רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*, that would definitely be a בכור *bechor*? What? Like the Koy's
case, like doesn't have the split hooves or something like that...
I don't know, yeah, I don't know.
What about טומטום ואנדרוגינוס *tumtum v'androgynus*? Is that considered a בכור *bechor*?
It doesn't matter though because... oh that's interesting. If you say that
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס *tumtum v'androgynus* is
a
מין בפני עצמו *min bifnei atzmo*, you're right, that would also... if
you say a טומטום ואנדרוגינוס *tumtum v'androgynus* is male or female and
you just don't know which, then you would put it into the
50/50. Right, but that's true, that's a good point. If... Michael said,
what about the case like טומטום ואנדרוגינוס *tumtum v'androgynus*, like the androgynous,
right? So that should also say less than 50% of all animals.
If you said that was a male or female, we just didn't
know which, then it would just mean that it is 50/50, we
just don't know which box to put this in. But you're
right, that's... that would have been a nice case to add to.
Okay, let's finish this up. ובמוקדשים תקבר *u'bimukdashim titkaver*, if it's sanctified
animals, you bury them because it doesn't matter male or female. מאי
טעמא *mai ta'ama*? What's the reason? רובו דמקדשו *rubo d'mikdashu*. Most of
them are sanctified. Not most, like 99.9% male or female, as long
as it's not some bizarre case like this נדמה *nidmeh* case. There,
the vast majority, and therefore you... regardless, you have to bury it.
ואין קוברין אותה *v'ein kovrin otah*... now, you do not bury it
by the crossroads because of דרכי אמורי Darkhei Emori, *darchei emori*. Now
we have an interesting גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. Michael says isn't it obvious?
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו
*Abaye v'Rava d'amri duvayhu*. אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* say it... both
say: כל דבר שיש בו רפואה refuah *kol davar sheyesh bo refuah*,
anything that is... that serves the purpose of health, אין בו משום
דרכי אמורי Darkhei Emori. *ein bo mishum darchei emori*, is not a
problem. אין בו משום רפואה ein bo mishum refuah *ein bo mishum
refuah*, if there is not an issue of health, יש בו yesh
bo. משום דרכי אמורי Darkhei Emori. *yesh bo mishum darchei emori*. Now
what does that mean to serve the purpose of health? Let's read
a line of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first and then I'll tell
you what רש"י *Rashi* says. Because in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it
actually is something that I think is a little more understandable. רש"י
*Rashi* brings... frames it in a particular way. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says like this: ותניא *v'tanya*, we turn in the ברייתא braita, *Braitah*,
אילן שמשיר פירותיו *ilan she'meshir peirotav*, if a fruit... if a tree
is dropping its fruits and you want to do something about it,
סוקרו בסיקרא *sokro besikra*, you can either clip... paint like some red
paint on it, or whatever, some paint, וטוענו באבנים *v'touno ba'avanim*, or
laden it down the branches with stones. And that's okay, that's not
דרכי אמורי Darkhei Emori. *darchei emori*, that's not considered to be like
magic. So בשלמא *bishlama*, the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, how does that
make sense? I understand וטוענו באבנים *v'touno ba'avanim*, you can laden it
with stones, כי היכי דניכחיש חיליה *ki heichi dinichish cheilei*, that it
should weaken its strength. Maybe the reason it's dropping fruit is there's
too much sap going through it and you do this type of
a thing and it somehow, you know, counteracts whatever... whatever the physical...
physical issues were that were causing that to happen. אלא סוקרו בסיקרא
מאי? Why can you like paint it with a paint? That seems
to be just total, you know, witchcraft or total, you know, whatever,
you know,
superstition or whatever it might be. So the גמרא Gemara says, כי
היכי דליחזו אינשי וליבעו עליה רחמי, ki heikhi delikhzu inshi veliv'u alei
rakhamei, because that way people will see it and they'll pray for
it. So prayer, that's different. Prayer works. Okay, כדתניא, kedetanya, we learned
in a ברייתא, וטמא טמא יקרא utamei tamei yikra by the מצורע.
metzora. People would call out טמא טמא. tamei tamei. צריך להודיע לרבים,
tsarikh lehodi'a lerabim, he has to inform the masses of his status
that he is a מצורע. metzora. ורבים מבקשים עליו רחמים, verabim mevakshim
alav rakhamim, and therefore people will pray for him. So you see
to announce the problem is not at all witchcraft, it's a way
of getting people to pray, and we believe in the efficacy of
prayer and that will address the problem. וכן, vekhen, and it ends
וכן מי שאירע בו דבר צריך להודיע לרבים. vekhen mi she'eira bo
davar tsarikh lehodi'a lerabim. If anybody has bad a tragedy or something
bad that's happened to him, you should tell people about it, not
just as a psychological advice says the גמרא, but ורבים מבקשים עליו
רחמים verabim mevakshim alav rakhamim and people will pray for you. אמר
רבינא, amar Ravina, כמאן תלינן קופסא בדיקלא? keman telinan kufsa bedikla? According
to whom do we suspend a like a cluster of dates on
a palm tree? If the palm tree is dropping its fruit, so
כמאן? keman? כי האי תנא, ki hai tanna, like this תנא tanna
that says that it is not a problem of דרכי אמורי, but
it's a סימן siman that lets people pray and therefore it's acceptable.
Now, what is the line between health and not health? So based
on the גמרא, I would have said, which certainly speaks to us,
that the line is something that can be explained rationally based on
the science as they knew it. So or, you know, based on
their
religious beliefs that leads to prayer and prayer whatever, but the idea
of you put on the stones is a rational explanation as their
science that that counteracted whatever the sap was and whatever the problem
was and that that's the difference between רפואה refuah and not רפואה
refuah, means something that makes scientific sense is not a problem of
דרכי אמורי. Look at רש"י. רש"י says, יש בו משום רפואה, yesh
bo mishum refuah, three lines from the bottom, says רש"י, כגון משקה
אותם, kegon mashkeh otam,
like a type of a drink, like you know of a potion
or a salve, או לחישה דלחיש אמרעא, o lakhisha delakhish amara,
or some incantation that you whisper over a that you whisper over
a wound. That's acceptable. That's not דרכי אמורי. The גמרא has a
lot of לחשים. lakhashim. So what is אין בו משום רפואה that's
a problem? כגון שעושין שלא על החולי, kegon she'osin shelo al hacholi,
it's not related to sickness, כגון קבורה שיהא בפרשת דרכים וכיוצא בהם
שדומים למנחשים. kegon k'vurah she'tehei befarashat drakhim vekhayotzei bahem shedomim limnakhshim. It's
not because anything is sick, it's just a way of warding off
evil spirits. So according to רש"י, which maybe is a little bit
more the language of the גמרא of יש בו משום רפואה, yesh
bo mishum refuah, depends what you mean יש בו. yesh bo, רש"י
says the issue is not the method used, the issue is what
problem you're coming to solve. If you're coming to solve a sickness
then there are lots of things that might help, even things like
incantations, that's not a problem. If it's just a general warding off
of spirits, that's דרכי אמורי. Obviously, you know, for us I think
that seems a little troublesome and I think within the גמרא, you
know, without getting into now about the about the incantations in the
גמרא, at least this גמרא's line could be יש בו, the emphasis
is not that it serves the purpose of רפואה, but whether it
really can be explained to be health-related meaning that there's a rational
explanation for it or a non-rational explanation for it. Okay, we'll answer.